<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pindarick poem consecrated to the memory of his much honoured friend, William Fox Esquire. Who died of the fatal small pox April 12, 1680. In the 19th year of his age. Dedicated to his most afflicted parents the right honourable Sir Stephen Fox knight, one of the lords commissioners of the treasury, clerk of the green cloath, &amp;c. and his most vertuous lady.</title>
            <author>Maidwell, Lewis, 1650-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M284A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217729</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829378</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1870:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pindarick poem consecrated to the memory of his much honoured friend, William Fox Esquire. Who died of the fatal small pox April 12, 1680. In the 19th year of his age. Dedicated to his most afflicted parents the right honourable Sir Stephen Fox knight, one of the lords commissioners of the treasury, clerk of the green cloath, &amp;c. and his most vertuous lady.</title>
                  <author>Maidwell, Lewis, 1650-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: L. Maidwell [i.e. Lewis Maidwell].</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Christ Church Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fox, William, 1660 or 61-1680 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="eulogy">
            <pb facs="tcp:33817:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A PINDARICK POEM, CONSECRATED To the Memory of his much Honoured Friend, WILLIAM FOX Eſquire.</head>
            <head type="sub">WHO DIED Of the Fatal ſmall Pox <hi>April</hi> 22, 1680. In the 19th. Year of his Age. Dedicated to his moſt afflicted Parents the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Stephen Fox</hi> Knight, one of the Lords Commiſſioners of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, Clerk of the Green Cloath, &amp;c. and his moſt Vertuous Lady.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AH Sir! they told me he was Dead,</l>
               <l>To prepar'd Joys, and endleſs Glories Fled.</l>
               <l>Oh my Prophetick Fears!</l>
               <l>The pointed news like Lightning pierc'd my Ears,</l>
               <l>Too great to be reliev'd with Cries and Tears.</l>
               <l>It quickly ran through every Part,</l>
               <l>It lick'd up Life in all my Veins,</l>
               <l>It ſhot new Tortures and new Pains,</l>
               <l>And like cold Death ſurpriz'd my trembling Heart.</l>
               <l>At length my ſtruggling Griefs their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilence Broke,</l>
               <l>And in their Pangs with great ſubmiſſion Spoke.</l>
               <l>Ah how dark to Humane Seiſe,</l>
               <l>Are the myſterious ways of Providence!</l>
               <l>Why ſhould ill Man waſt long, and pleaſant Lives?</l>
               <l>Enjoy their Friends, their Children, and their Wives?</l>
               <l>Who cauſe the Widdows Groans, and Orphans Tears,</l>
               <l>And live to count their Vices, with their Years.</l>
               <l>Whilſt the young Man, his great Creators Praiſe,</l>
               <l>Fam'd for ripe Virtues in his greener Days,</l>
               <l>By Strangers much careſs'd, and much Admir'd,</l>
               <l>Much lov'd by all his Friends, but more Deſir'd,</l>
               <l>Like ſome fair Flower ſoon Withers, and Decaies</l>
               <l>Amongſt ten thouſand Weeds, which thrive, but Yield</l>
               <l>No Profit to the Maſter of the Field.</l>
               <l>Though by the Bed the Pious Mother Rears,</l>
               <l>Her penſive Soul upon the Wings of Prayers,</l>
               <l>That gentle Heaven would grant him a Reprieve,</l>
               <l>Alas in vain ſhe rends the Skies,</l>
               <l>No Prayers, nor Tears can Life Retrieve,</l>
               <l>For the good Youth graſps her dear Hand, and Dies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>[2]</head>
               <l>How ſecretly Heaven manages Mankind!</l>
               <l>And out of kindneſs keeps is Blind.</l>
               <l>In all its penal Laws,</l>
               <l>It gives th' Effect, but veils the mighty Cauſe.</l>
               <l>Tis hard, but puniſh'd Man muſt not complain,</l>
               <l>Or if he does tis but in Vain,</l>
               <l>For ſtruggling doth but cloſer draw the Chain.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:33817:2"/>
               <l>Hence 'tis more eaſie, as 'tis Good,</l>
               <l>In the ſharp Torments of our Fleſh, and Blood,</l>
               <l>To bear the ſtroaks with Patience, and to Truſt</l>
               <l>Thoſe Diſpenſations, though obſcure, yet Juſt.</l>
               <l>Ah Madam, let me firſt my pardon Crave,</l>
               <l>Before I bring you to his Grave,</l>
               <l>And on the hallow'd Tomb Expreſs,</l>
               <l>The Figure of your once great Happineſs.</l>
               <l>Then let your Grief find Eaſe, and ſome Content,</l>
               <l>To think your Son di'd Young, and Innocent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>[3]</head>
               <l>Indeed he did afford a lovely <hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here, pleaſant Fields adorn'd with cheerful Green,</l>
               <l>And early Flowers ollig'd the Eye,</l>
               <l>With Natures primitive Simpicity.</l>
               <l>There, Artificial Currents did appear,</l>
               <l>With Muſick running, and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h deepneſs Clear.</l>
               <l>Which being cut with greateſt Art, and Toil,</l>
               <l>Did beautifie the View, and fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en all the Soil.</l>
               <l>From theſe fair Streams, the fruitful Trees that Grew</l>
               <l>Upon the ſmiling Barks, renew</l>
               <l>Their cheerful ſtrength, and as the Waters paſs,</l>
               <l>Rejoyce to ſee themſelves within the liquid Glaſs.</l>
               <l>A Rich fair Hill did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>and hard by,</l>
               <l>Climb'd up with eaſe by him, though very High,</l>
               <l>From whoſe larg Top, he might as twere from Home,</l>
               <l>Take a true Scheme of life to come.</l>
               <l>Honours though diſtant ſeem'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be at Hand</l>
               <l>Within his reach, and ready at Command.</l>
               <l>Beneath this Hill was drawn a Valley Low,</l>
               <l>There the freſheſt Virtues Grow,</l>
               <l>Humility and Condeſcention too.</l>
               <l>'Tis there Mankind takes moſt Delight,</l>
               <l>And beſt from it obſerves the Mountains Height.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>[4]</head>
               <l>But whilſt our Eyes were Bleſt</l>
               <l>With this kind Proſpect Cruel Fate</l>
               <l>Demonſtrated this Truth, that ſmall Content</l>
               <l>Ought to be plac'd in humane State.</l>
               <l>For lo! the Calm and Glorious day was Spent</l>
               <l>And the bright Sun ſoon hurry'd to the Weſt.</l>
               <l>Ah Fatal ſight! within my View,</l>
               <l>The Croaking Raven to the Forreſt Flew,</l>
               <l>And after him the Screeching Owle,</l>
               <l>With the Foreboding Jay,</l>
               <l>Pitch'd on the Top of the unlucky Yew.</l>
               <l>Whilſt underneath the Rav'nous Wolf did Howl,</l>
               <l>Deſirous of its Prey,</l>
               <l>Glad to behold the Conqueſt of the Day.</l>
               <l>Now horrid Night came Marching up apace,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33817:2"/>
               <l>And with black fumes infected all the Place.</l>
               <l>How quickly all things chang'd, ſeem'd Flat, and Dead,</l>
               <l>In Haſt each Form retir'd, each Beauty Fled,</l>
               <l>And the delightfull Landskip Vaniſhed.</l>
               <l>Then Groans, and Shreeks were heard, and Showers of Rain</l>
               <l>Deſcending feircely down, Waſh'd all the Neighb'ring Plain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>[5]</head>
               <l>Twas a ſad change! And as my Grief's are True,</l>
               <l>Pray Madam let me weep with You.</l>
               <l>If I forget Thee, my much Honour'd Friend,</l>
               <l>Till life worn out ſhall reach its deſir'd End.</l>
               <l>Oh! may no real Friend of Mine,</l>
               <l>So much my worldly good Deſign,</l>
               <l>As thou didſt freely Vow to be,</l>
               <l>A faithfull profitable Friend to Me.</l>
               <l>For which kind promiſe Dear, and Generou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Youth,</l>
               <l>As I am ſure thy words were born of Truth</l>
               <l>So I will gratefully remember Thee;</l>
               <l>Often with Silent ſteps I'le come,</l>
               <l>To vent my Grief at thy ſad Tomb,</l>
               <l>Thy Bodies ſecond Womb:</l>
               <l>But chiefly on that Lamentable Day,</l>
               <l>When thy chaſt Soul made haſt away,</l>
               <l>I will my Melancholy Sonnets Sing,</l>
               <l>And ſcatter there my Flow'ry Offering<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Thy Grave like Thee ſhall imitate the Spring.</l>
               <l>On thy beloved Relicks I will Strew,</l>
               <l>The bluſhing Roſe, and Violet Blew;</l>
               <l>Thee Hyacinth, and thee Narciſſus Too.</l>
               <l>For once he was more ſweet, and freſh than You.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>[6]</head>
               <l>As for thy Soul tis now at Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</l>
               <l>Happy with Saints, with Angels Bleſt;</l>
               <l>Freed by thy new Immortal Birth,</l>
               <l>From that allay of our Contagious Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</l>
               <l>Safe from the world, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l its Snares,</l>
               <l>From its light joys, and hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y cares,</l>
               <l>From painted Sepulchers, and Gilded Pills,</l>
               <l>From Smooth beginnings, and their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Ills.</l>
               <l>Nay Heaven was kind to call Thee h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me ſo Soon,</l>
               <l>And lodge thee in thy Inn before twas Noon.</l>
               <l>Elſe hadſt thou ventur'd on thy danger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Way,</l>
               <l>In a long Journey, and the heat of Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Though thou as yet wert very cool and Pure;</l>
               <l>Yet who on earth can be Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure?</l>
               <l>Perhaps ſome Malady had ſeiz'd thy S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul,</l>
               <l>Perhaps had pitted it and made it Foul</l>
               <l>Or elſe ſome Thief joyning himſelf to Thee,</l>
               <l>Under pretence of Fatal Company,</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33817:3"/>
               <l>Perhaps had lead thy better ſence aſtray,</l>
               <l>And made at laſt thy Innocence a Prey.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>[7]</head>
               <l>But now henceforth for ever Young,</l>
               <l>Ever Powerful, ever Strong,</l>
               <l>Ever Vertuous, and ſecure of Bliſs,</l>
               <l>With ſuch Companions as thy Brother <hi>Daphnis</hi> is.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daphnis,</hi> than whom none is more Gay, or bright,</l>
               <l>Amongſt the fair Inhabitants of Light,</l>
               <l>The Joyful <hi>Daphnis</hi> clap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d his Wings, and Said,</l>
               <l>But ſpake it with a Smile,</l>
               <l>Brother tis well, our Parents call us Dead,</l>
               <l>And that you ſtaid behind ſo ſhort a While.</l>
               <l>Like me on Earth you dwelt without its Crimes,</l>
               <l>But Heaven in mercy took you Home,</l>
               <l>To reſcue you from Sins of Preſent Times,</l>
               <l>And from the Puniſhmen of thoſe to Come.</l>
               <l>Here we enjoy Eternal Health,</l>
               <l>Eternal peace Eternal Wealth.</l>
               <l>Hither our Parents ev'ry Day make Haſt,</l>
               <l>And Hither all good Friends on Earth ſhall come at Laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>[8]</head>
               <l>Ah ye Bleſt Immortal Pare!</l>
               <l>Moſt bleſt becauſe ye dwell together there.</l>
               <l>Look down, and if you c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, with Pity, Know</l>
               <l>The wretched ſtate of Morals here below.</l>
               <l>Behold how ev'ry Age does run,</l>
               <l>Driv'n by peculiar Vice to be undone,</l>
               <l>Head-long into it own Confuſion.</l>
               <l>This Young-man gives his heart to looſe Deſires,</l>
               <l>And burns it up to Droſs, in lawleſs Fires.</l>
               <l>That, with his Wine pow'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out his precious Day,</l>
               <l>Drown's his Eſtate, and wiſhes Health away.</l>
               <l>Ambition grants Mans middle Age no Reſt,</l>
               <l>The Viper always gnaws his Ulcer'd Breſt;</l>
               <l>For a falſe fame, he will his ſoul Enſnare,</l>
               <l>Come ſhort of Heaven, for Caſtles in the Air.</l>
               <l>But miſerable Old age catches Hold,</l>
               <l>On the lov'd Canvaſs, to ado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e its Gold.</l>
               <l>On uſeleſs Wealth the broodin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Miſer lies,</l>
               <l>Turn'd into native Earth, bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re he Dies.</l>
               <l>Therefore the longer Man ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ances Age;</l>
               <l>He does but change his Vice, and tread another Stage.</l>
               <l>Hence old, and conſcious Sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers fear to die,</l>
               <l>For groſs Souls clog'd with Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, can never Fly.</l>
               <l>Or their ſhort wings grow weary, and can't move</l>
               <l>To the high Palace of the Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Above,</l>
               <l>But flutter in the lower Regions of the Sky.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>L. MAIDWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
